Finding Aid for Latin American Solidarity Committee Records 1970-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Latin American Solidarity Committee Records 1970-1989
Latin American Solidarity Committee.
1 linear feet
Group of University of Michigan students and other Ann Arbor, Michigan, residents formed to support progressive causes in Latin America and oppose U.S. government policies there; flyers, posters, press releases, position papers, photographs, and the group's journal La Palabra; also collected records of predecessor organization, Science for the People, and Farm Labor Organizing Committee, a support group within SFP.
89489 Bj 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received in September 1989. (Donor No. 7719 )
The collection is open for research.
The University of Michigan Latin American Solidarity Committee (L.A.S.C.) was formed in 1981 by students. Their common goals were to support the struggles of Latin American peoples against repressive and authoritarian political regimes, and to encourage the establishment of democratic government in Latin American countries. To this end, the committee endeavored to increase awareness of contemporary political and social realities in Latin America, and to pressure the United States government to change its military, political, and economic policies with regard to the region.
Predecessor and, to a certain extent, parent to the Latin American Solidarity Committee was the radical, Boston-based Science for the People. The group's interests centered on the political aspects of science, and the effects of science on the lives of people around the world. The Ann Arbor chapter of Science for the People was formed in 1974 by seven graduate students and faculty in biology at the University of Michigan. A central figure in the organization and activities of the chapter was Biology Professor John Vandermeer.
The activities of the Ann Arbor chapter of Science for the People took place on three levels. First, the group was involved in national-level discussions of issues, and provided ideas for the organization of Science for the People at the national level. "Internal Discussion Bulletins" and National Conferences were the major forum for this exchange of ideas. Second, the chapter was involved in activities at the regional level. These included participating in midwest regional conferences, sitting on regional coordinating committees and editorial collectives, as well as producing special issues of the national magazine, Science for the People. Third, the chapter sponsored activities locally. Activity groups were formed to discuss and analyze specific issues/topics in science and technology (e.g.--sexism in science, nuclear policy, and recombinant DNA) and to act on these analyses, if they felt so compelled. Other local activities included general meetings, a film series, and a 1976 Symposium on Biological Determinism, which spawned a mini-course and a book entitled Biology as a Social Weapon (available at the University of Michigan Natural Sciences Library).
One of the more active groups in Science for the People was the Farm Labor Organizing Committee (FLOC) Support Group. Formed as a Science for the People activity group in 1977, the FLOC Support Group became semi-autonomous and aligned its activities with those of the national FLOC organization, based in Toledo, Ohio. The Ann Arbor group was started with the idea that the resources of the University of Michigan could be used to help FLOC start a migrant workers' health clinic and to aid in FLOC's corporate relations. However, most of the group's activity involved becoming familiar with the plight of migrant farmworkers in Ohio, Michigan, and Indiana, and providing practical support for the Toledo organization mainly through the use of publicity. The Ann Arbor group was primarily interested in the use of pesticides and their effects on the health of farm workers, and they helped produce pamphlets which served to inform the workers of the potential dangers of pesticides.
Both the University of Michigan Science for the People chapter and the FLOC Support Group actively participated in a nationwide boycott of the Campbell Soup and Libby's companies beginning in 1979. The boycott was a response to the companies' apparent failure to recognize the rights of farmworkers to engage in collective bargaining. The boycott persisted until 1986, when FLOC's Toledo office reached a contract agreement with the companies.
After 1986, the two local groups became moribund. L.A.S.C., which grew out of their activities and co-existed with them for several years, continues to be active.
The records of the Latin American Solidarity Committee comprise five series: Latin American Solidarity Committee (1981-1989); Science for the People (1970-1983); Ann Arbor FLOC Support Group (1979-1985); Miscellaneous Organizations (1977-1985); and Photographs. The records span from 1970 to 1989, but the bulk of the material falls between 1974 and 1983. The majority of the records represent the Science for the People series. The files are arranged alphabetically by topic within each series.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor Science for the People (Organization); Social action--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Farm Labor Organizing Committee (Ohio); Latin America.; Latin American Solidarity Committee.; Migrant agricultural laborers.; Science for the People (Organization); University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor Science for the People (Organization); Demonstrations.; Veterans Administration Hospital (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Latin American Solidarity Committee
  The Latin American Solidarity Committee series (5 folders) includes materials which give an excellent overview of the concerns of the group. La Palabra, a journal published 3-4 times per year, conveys information regarding current events in Latin American countries, and details the activities of the group itself in response to those events. The "Press Releases and Position Papers" include brief synopses of the group's attitudes towards American state and national political figures such as Perry Bullard, Carl Pursell, Jeanne Kirkpatrick, and George Bush. It also contains items relating to specific issues in countries within the group's interest, such as Cuba, El Salvador, Guatemala, and Haiti.
  - Flyers and Posters (Box 1)
  - La Palabra: journal of the L.A.S.C., 1981-1989, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Press releases and position papers (Box 1)
- Science for the People
  The Science for the People series (30 folders, .5 linear feet) contains records which document not only the activities of the Ann Arbor chapter, but also those of the regional and national levels of the organization. "Internal Discussion Bulletins," "National Conferences," and "National Newsletters," contain materials generated at the national level. They are valuable because they provide a context for the activities of the Ann Arbor chapter in relation to the Boston headquarters and the other chapters around the country. The "Internal Discussion Bulletins" are especially helpful in understanding the goals and activities of the organization at the national as well as local levels. They include chapter reports, discourse on problems of national and local organization, and discussion of issues which were of interest to Science for the People.
  The correspondence and minutes of the "Midwest Editorial Collective" offer the most complete record of the Ann Arbor chapter's involvement in regional activities. Subjects covered include regional conferences and publication of special issues of the Science for the People magazine. Also valuable to a study of the group's regional activities is the "Midwest Coordinating Committee" file, which documents that committee's attempts to facilitate the formation and growth of other Midwest chapters, and to promote inter-chapter communication. The Midwest Region Newsletter includes coverage of regional conferences, regional chapter reports, and updates on special magazine issues being produced by the Midwest Editorial Collective.
  The best introduction to the group's local activities can be found in the "History and Statement of Purpose" file. It contains a historical sketch, produced in 1977, and a statement of purpose, which briefly summarize chapter activities. The "Ann Arbor Chapter Minutes, Newsletter, and Chapter Reports" file documents the group's day-to-day activities and discussion. The different types of materials are combined because they are highly complementary. Even together, however, they provide far from comprehensive coverage. Development of articles and format for the magazine are the major topics covered in the "Correspondence" file.
  - "American Biology Teacher" article: correspondence and draft 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Chapter Minutes, Newsletter, and Chapter Reports 1970-1981 (Box 1)
  - Biology as a Social Weapon: symposium book
    - Correspondence with potential publishers 1976 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with publisher: Burgess 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Marketing 1977 (Box 1)
    - Prospectus and Introduction (Box 1)
  - China Study Group 1977 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: general 1975-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Cuba Study Group 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Films 1980 (Box 1)
  - Flyers (Box 1)
  - History, Statements of Purpose 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Internal Discussion Bulletin: national
    - 1974-1976 no. 1- (Box 1)
    - 1977-1979 -no.14 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1982 nos. 15-19 (Box 1)
  - Midwest Editorial Collective: regional
    - Correspondence 1978-1982 (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1982 (Box 1)
  - Midwest Region Newsletter, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Midwest Regional Coordinating Committee 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - Military Series 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - National Conferences 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - National Newsletter 1982 (Box 1)
  - Nuclear Policy Group 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Population: criticism of Garrett Hardin 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Recombinant DNA Group 1976 (Box 1)
  - Science Teaching Group 1977 (Box 1)
  - Sexism in Science Group 1977 (Box 1)
  - Symposium: Biological Determinism 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - V.A. Nurses Support Committee 1977 (Box 1)
- Farm Labor Organizing Committee (FLOC) Support Group
  The records of the Farm Labor Organizing Committee (FLOC) Support Group series (16 folders) largely concern the Campbell/Libby's boycott. The first two files of the series, "Boycott (Campbell and Libby's)" and "Boycott Retreat", are especially interesting. The former contains correspondence between the Ann Arbor group and the companies, and the latter is an outline of the group's boycott strategy. The "Minutes" address the day-to-day activities and administration of the Ann Arbor group, and cover topics such as picketing, fund-raising, and the group's slide show, "Machines, Migrants & Monopolies." "Farm Labor Research Project" pertains to a project in which some FLOC Support Group members worked with members of the New World Agriculture Group. The project, started in 1982, focused on the study of such problems as pesticide use. The file here provides little information regarding the Ann Arbor group's involvement, but contains information on the history and purpose of the project.
  - Boycott: Campbell and Libby's 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Boycott Retreat 1981 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and Articles (Box 1)
  - Farm Labor Research Project Statement of Purpose and Resolutions 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Flyers and Songs (Box 1)
  - Funding: Rackham and MSA 1979-1985 (Box 1)
  - Health Clinic/Food Pamphlets 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Label Campaign: Campbell 1980 (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1979-1985, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - National Support Committees (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1980 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Slide Show: "Machines, Migrants, & Monopolies"; correspondence, draft scripts, flyers 1980 (Box 1)
  - Union Endorsements 1979 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Organizations
  Included in the Miscellaneous Organizations series (5 folders) are various materials dealing with organizations in Michigan with which L.A.S.C., Science for the People, and the FLOC Support Group were peripherally involved or ideologically related. The Michigan Farmworkers Ministry Coalition, the Michigan chapter of IMAGE (a national Hispanic organization), and the Michigan Alliance for Disarmament are most notably represented.
  - Farmworkers Organizations in Michigan 1979-1985 (Box 1)
    (includes Michigan Farmworkers Ministry, Michigan Farmworker Ministry Coalition, and United Farm Workers of America AFL-CIO)
  - IMAGE: national organization concerned with government employment for Spanish-speaking peoples 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Alliance for Disarmament, Organizational Description and Conference on Disarmament May 1982 (Box 1)
  - Ujamaa: joint newsletter of the Ann Arbor chapters of the African Students Association and the Southern Africa Liberation Committee, April 1977 (Box 1)
- Photographs (Box 1)
  The Photographs series (1 folder) is comprised of 13 black and white photographs. The subject of the images is the July 1977 rally held at the Veteran's Administration Hospital in Ann Arbor in support of two Hispanic nurses who had been fired. These photographs should be used in conjunction with the materials in the "V.A. Nurses Support Committee" file, in the Science for the People series.
  - Rally for V.A. Nurses Narcisco and Perez July 1977